Hello! Today we will understand Le Chatelier's principle and see
what effect increasing pressure has on this chemical equilibrium.
Here we have a container with reactants and products in
equilibrium. Notice that the reactant side has 3 moles of
gas, and the product side has 2 moles.
Now imagine we double the pressure on this system.
When we do this, the container's volume becomes half.
When volume decreases, the concentration of each gas increases. Therefore,
the concentration of all reactants and products will immediately increase.
According to this, Option A is absolutely correct.
However, Le Chatelier's principle states that the system will oppose this
change. To reduce pressure, equilibrium will shift in the direction where
there are fewer gas moles, that is, in the forward direction.
One very important point: the equilibrium constant 'K'
only changes with temperature, not with pressure. Therefore,
options C and D are directly wrong.
So both A and B are sort of correct, but the first
and most direct result of increasing pressure is the increase in concentration.
The shift happens afterwards. Therefore, Option A is the most accurate answer.
I hope you have understood this concept. Thank you!